hi welcome back to lum rim and it's good
to see you this morning
uh the the crew here is very bright and
and
uh very awake and shiny
right not really
okay uh so we're gonna go ahead
uh go ahead through this we're we're
just finishing up
the part by the way i remember to speak
slowly okay
we're just finishing up the part
uh where we talk about if you are
trying to get bodhichitta
if you're working on that then less
obstacles will come in your life okay
less problems will come
all right and here's one last
statement about it and then we're going
to move on to the next benefit
okay uh we're at the
okay you tibetan guys button they are
distracted by
pastries it's cruel to eat them in front
of guests
what did he do that was famous
he wrote a famous history of buddhism
early buddhism
which is a which by the way we don't
have early histories of buddhism
uh and and they don't exist
so we're lucky that he wrote something
we don't otherwise we won't know about
india but what else did he do
yeah he put the kanye tenure together
which is small thing
3700 surviving books from india
which john brady's project input
uh the first thing they did was to input
that it took about 12 years
or something and it was extraordinary
it's really extraordinary it has never
existed like that
okay is the honorific for to be
sick so and we say now all right
to be sick but he's being polite
when his honorable body was sick cup
gyalse rimbache this is again uh
tog me [__] this bodhisattva
who lived in tibet about 700 years ago
then dungney he invited him to to his
room
gombe and told me [__]
they'll say his real name is kelsey told
me some more
uh he sat in the corner and meditated
about bodhichitta
uh pembe logyu logyu means there's a
story
that burton rinpoche felt much much
better by having someone in the room
just meditating about bodhichitta
this very very famous teacher
felt better by the way son kappa didn't
meet him directly and he used to
complain about it
he missed him by three years or
something not by many years
so he studied with his students but he
never got to study with bhutan
okay
problems and obstacles in your life
can't touch you or they will be less
strong opinion
and you know i can tell you from my own
experience
many many years of trying to practice
when you get a problem especially
it could be like i don't know a new
government rule or
it could be a problem with another
person
in a group and and from many many years
of experience i can tell you have a
choice
you know you cannot sleep that night
you know you can be grumpy your
sleepover
be disturbed i think so that's one
choice
you know or uh you can
you can think about bodhichitta for them
and it's not
uh natural it's artificial
it doesn't feel natural you know it's
like
okay this person suddenly joined our
group
they are giving me problems you know
and then you start your mind starts
making up stories about them and
things you should say to them and then i
from many years experience i can tell
you
if you just focus on bodhichitta at that
moment
uh the whole thing goes away
if you just try to love them like their
mother
the whole thing goes away and then
20 minutes later you start having the
same thoughts again and then you have to
do the body
thing again okay and
so that's just from many years of
experience it's true
that even a very artificial body tutor
can make your life so much easier okay
especially when you have troubles or
problems semdi gompe
me ming nepe mitsupa
uh and a lot of those
you know times when you can't sleep at
night because you had a problem with
somebody
in the afternoon uh are not due to that
person
they are due to uh
like praetors or people who have died
already
being spirit beings so it's not a
superstition it's real
they exist they watch you having trouble
with somebody
and then they just float around your
they float around you for hours you know
so you have to understand there's
there's other people involved when you
can't sleep at night and you're thinking
about a problem or something
there's actually beings who are
disturbed
and they're floating around you and then
if you
think about bodhichitta especially for
those
troublemakers beings then the whole
thing disappears
okay and you have a good sleep
especially during the alarm room class
just kidding
he said check it out choke means allow
this choke choke can mean ritual like
choga
and cho
hey check it out just try it next time
you can't sleep because someone's
bothering you you know
be aware that it could be these other
beings and
and and try to love them actively
and you'll see the whole thing turn
around and you'll have a nice sleep
okay we're moving on to benefit number
nine
uh which is that we will quickly finish
salam say solemn it's not
arabic okay it's what sar
the levels and paths levels and paths
okay how many levels
10 how many lumps five
okay so solemn and by the way there's an
open solemn and there's a secret solemn
and uh was it course six
in the diamond mountain uh diamond way
course
uh is is the secret solo
okay so you can finish either set of
solemns
more quickly if you have bodhichitta
okay and
there's a picture of a
person at the top this person finished
the
song when i think of saw when i think of
the spiritual
levels and i think of getting to the top
of the tenth one
uh then then you can have this picture
in your mind
okay guppanee guppa means benefit number
nine
chanchu gi san may patoni
let's say you just focus on
emptiness and by the way we're going to
have a heavy heavy
emptiness long rim retreat in
what month soon in the summer
and actually it's already prepared the
whole thing is prepared it was an
incredible amount of work
you know uh last month uh i got it ready
and
uh it's i think uh eight chapters
it's a third of the chapters from the
guardian's most difficult work
and it's extraordinarily beautiful
okay but if you just
focus on emptiness and you don't
think about other people right
and you meet people like that i used to
meet them at princeton they were in the
philosophy department
and philosophy and religion i was in the
religion department but um
[Music]
we had to share the same building
because we weren't important
we didn't make money from the government
uh
like the physics department tony guitar
if all you do is study nagarjuna like we
are going to do
this year and it's going to be an
amazing course
yes you're only going to get the yeshik
and not the tsunami and don't forget
that's the prayer that you
make every time you have a class
yeah the collection of wisdom and the
collection of merit
collection of wisdom creates your
buddha mind in the collection of merit
creates your
buddha body okay good so
the main buddha body collector is your
bodhichitta
and the main buddha mind collector is
your emptiness understanding okay so
what's he saying here
if you just focus on emptiness and you
don't
try to be nice to other people you're
gonna have a
misbalanced body you have a big head
and no body okay
all right uh suck minila soak me you
need both of them
okay by the way what's
so a code word for
for fifty dollars when you say the two
collections
what's it a code word for what would you
normally call
salt
karma we talked about it but it was a
long we talked about a long time ago
like two days ago
yeah karma means dirty karma which is
what we make
the seeds we make are dirty karma seeds
that turn you into a buddha
body or mine we don't call him karma
anymore we call him salt
sambar in in sanskrit and we're gonna
he's gonna talk about it
all right
[Music]
uh how are you gonna how you gonna
collect the two collections
and how you gonna get here's a hundred
dollar question tim woke up
what's the two obstacles
of your negative emotions and obstacles
to omniscience okay
i always thought it for 300
why is that seems to be a misnomer
why does the name seem to be a little
messed up 300
the two obstacles there's a there's a
problem there
already
200.
[Music]
yeah good 200 bucks for tim
he's making money this morning yay see
the karma of helping
to run the whole thing all right uh
well not helping actually running the
whole thing okay
yeah to get rid of those two obstacles
and the seeds and the seeds for the two
obstacles
so you need
chianchuki sam here's another hundred
dollars i'm in a mood this morning
okay he says
strangely he doesn't say you need
bodhichitta
he says you need fake bodhichitta
not that easy
hey god you made 500 bucks already this
morning
you're so hot we're gonna repeat it
again
he says look if you don't want to have a
mis-shaped body with a big head and no
body but
if you want to be a buddha with a fat
head and no body
then go ahead and don't work on your
booty chewing
and if you don't want to get rid of both
obstacles
then don't work on your body tuner and
by the way
don't forget that the body part
comes from about each other but then he
says
fake body china and fake body children
is is a word that they use because
there's two kinds of bodhichitta
in which tim won the how much was it
50 cents he won the money this morning
uh
there's two kinds of bodhichitta
ultimate bodhichitta
is what tim the direct perception of
emptiness okay
the and that's an interesting idea
perhaps the greatest kindness you can
ever pay to other people
is to see emptiness directly okay and
then
still you could have another bodhichitta
which we call fake or
deceptive because it's still dealing
with normal reality
not because it's not real uh and that
one will create your buddha body
okay mainly all right all right
and we have a picture here
i'm in a good mood hundred dollars
what's the picture
what am i trying to say with the picture
damn 600 bucks for tim this morning
actually i tell him all the questions
before class and
then we split the money
[Laughter]
yeah it's a bird with one wing okay and
it's a very famous example in buddhism
you know if you've ever seen a bird with
a broken wing
you know they just kind of flop around
in a circle and if you just worked on
emptiness
and didn't work on bodhichitta you would
be like a bird with only one wing
yeah okay you need both wings okay
this is a very powerful statement samdi
yuna
if you get to bodhichitta if you learn
to jump planets
sangha ki you can use tantra
you can use this diamond way say chiclet
sanya
you can become a buddha in one lifetime
if you have bodhichitta
okay if you have bodhichino then you can
practice diamond way
or medicine buddha or vagiogini or tara
and then in one lifetime you will knew
you can become a buddha kyung what's
[Music]
he's always saying that but you could be
a buddha
but why okay tell me why not
be mana if you don't have bodhichitta
sorry naki you can practice
those tantras nak means mantra right
darnani
you can practice mantras you can
practice
secret teachings take change
you won't even get to the first
tiny part of the first of the five paths
you won't reach the first tiny part
of the first of the five paths there's
five paths
there's five stages you go through
there's
five stages that every living being goes
through
in their spiritual development seeing
emptiness is the third one
reaching nirvana and or buddhahood is
the fifth one
the first one is just the beginning of
your spiritual
career and if you don't have bodhichitta
you could practice tantra but you won't
reach here
you won't reach the beginning of the fif
of the first path
okay he's putting he's
pretty powerful okay we have a
picture there i don't know i was trying
to find a picture of uh
starting walking down a path
and it's like your foot is in the air
and you haven't stepped down on the
first stone
uh if you if you try to practice tantra
but you don't work on your body chitta
you don't work on alarm room
then you'll be like a person who's
always standing
with their foot in the air and hasn't
even stepped on the path yet
okay all right okay
therefore we can say
that the place to start for all dharma
practice
is bodhichitta all right and then he
gives this beautiful
example say
let's do it again one two three
okay it means uh the french fried
practice who can tell me for zero
dollars
yeah go to mcdonald's buy the only thing
you can eat there
guess what they have salads i said
something you can eat
don't tell veronica yeah and then break
little pieces of
french fries often and throw them to
burn and and do this prayer
that they become your disciple in the
future it's it's really fun
and by the way buddhism should be fun if
your buddhism is not fun
you're doing something wrong okay should
be fun
all right even using buddhism with
irritating people
should be fun okay
then everything you do if you have
bodhichitta
just giving a french fry to a bird
is your daily practice okay that's daily
practice
you don't have to work so hard just go
to mcdonald's
eat french fries and throw them at birth
with bodhichitta okay you're just one
bird but i'm doing this for all the
birds okay
all right you will come
if you act that way if your buddhist
practice is fun and
if you keep doing it with in every part
of the day
even when you're relaxing i'm gonna
watch this
netflix movie for all living beings
then okay you it's practice okay
uh salam yod you will complete the
levels and pass and he stops
after only a page and a half or
something okay that benefit
he doesn't talk more about it and and i
wonder why
sometimes i wonder why sometimes you see
something in the alarm room
and you're like some of those
cool things he spent 10 15 pages on them
here he spent like half a page is it not
important that that this can help you
complete all the levels and pass
why did he shorten you know
i think the internet went out
i mean you never know right you never
know why stuff happens in a
in a scripture it could be something
like that i don't know they ran out of
tampa or something okay tim and
jordan had to go to the grocery store in
wilcox
sorry about that and i'm very grateful
by me okay
all right so he finished the section uh
and uh here's a picture of a baby bird
okay and
i don't know i i
sometime i feed a lot of birds at home
especially during cocon
because i don't have much else to do and
uh
sometimes i get a baby bird falls out of
a nest and
and there's whole instructions online
how to feed them
with an eyedropper and uh
and i was doing that and and drop by
drop going in and i'm like
okay you're gonna be my student so i
didn't have french fries
and i was using water and you can do
that okay
all right next benefit uh
number 10 okay and this
is the longest one like we're i think
we're halfway through the
retreat or roughly and then this is the
longest benefit this is gonna take the
rest of the
of the retreat all right
and and the word is very beautiful it
says
you will become the garden where all
living beings grow their happiness
okay you will become the garden so i
have a garden
i finally went on my first vacation as
an adult
and uh gelser came and watered at the
garden
and uh
you you become a garden for other
people's happiness okay
you become the garden you become the
earth
which feeds all the other people here's
a picture okay
and we've been talking about that idea
especially because pachi is here and
he's the biochar master of the universe
and uh if if
when you look at this picture you know
you just think oh it looks like a nice
little farm or something
but i want you to think about the
this black soil beneath the
harvest beneath the crops that you see
in this picture
beneath these green fields is a
hard-working biochar
here's the soil it's doing all the work
you know
the the crops is not the big deal
the soil is the big deal the soil is
working for everybody
so try to get that in your mind okay
we all eat uh much of what we eat is
grown
by farmers
but somebody else is behind the scenes
and that's the dirt that's the soil
we think about it in arizona because we
don't have any
we just have rocks uh but if you think
about it
the this black soil under the plant
is quietly feeding everybody
you know and if that soil were gone we
would all die okay
so this nobody gives credit to the soil
nobody goes and picks up dirt and says
thank you
they just sweep it out of their house
and complain about it
but the soil's keeping us all alive okay
and
bodhichitta is like that soil
and it's keeping everybody alive okay
bodhichitta is what runs the universe
behind the scenes okay so if you get
body chitter
you become that quiet fertile soil
which feeds the whole world it's a very
beautiful
picture you have to try to get it in
your mind okay
all right i used to think all food was
grown at the grocery store
but uh anyway if you meet a gardener and
they will
teach you about it
okay you gotta repeat this one okay you
ready
take a deep breath
just repeat the words don't sit there
silent
okay one two three
[Music]
good opening lines of entering the
middle way the opening lines
of entering the middleweight uh umala
say umala okay
in sanskrit madhya
makkah avatara madhyamakavatara
okay entering the midway for a hundred
dollars
what's the middle way in this case
[Music]
come on okay cancel the bit
middleway here is a is a nickname
for negotiate wisdom okay
it's not the middle way philosophically
it's the book called the middle way
which is a nickname for the most
important book ever written on emptiness
which is called wisdom okay
and that's what we're going to study in
the next retreat
it's amazing it's a miracle you get to
study the mother book of all emptiness
and it's hard
and it's beautiful okay and no one ever
understood it since
1800 years ago so what happened
somebody wrote yeah a commentary called
getting into the middle way how to get
into the middleweight
okay so kappa wrote a
commentary to that called the sea of
emptiness
and then tony lama had to write a book
called
a ship for traveling on the sea of
emptiness
so you got four books okay got it here's
the middle way called
which is a nickname for wisdom
by
comes along about 450 years later
and says hey i'll help you get into it
okay and then some compasses it's like
an
ocean i'll show you those
27 short chapters of poetry
are really an ocean of wisdom he writes
a huge commentary
and then chonin llama oh by the way
tonka is
uh i call it 750 years after
chandi kirti who wrote this one and then
johnny lama comes along
275 years after tsukapa and says look
you need a boat for that ocean or you're
gonna drown
in tonkapa okay and we're
we're translating it okay and i'm
working really hard on translating we've
done about 600 pages are finished okay
so you people coveting at me about other
work i didn't do
i'm busy okay and if i don't do it no
one's gonna do it
so you know stop convincing on me but
anyway nobody's gonna stop okay
uh so these are the opening lines we got
a picture i think of chandra kitty
for twenty dollars what's the most
common mistake
about chanda kyuti twenty dollar
question it must be kind of easy
they mix them up with diamond candy okay
there's two cuties okay there's actually
three
for fifty dollars who's the third one
sumati kirti which is
son okay there's three kitties
okay so don't mix up the first two qt's
people do it all the time
in fact the library of congress
uh used to mix it up and i used to laugh
about it
this is the main library of the united
states and they constantly mix them up
so uh anyway chanda kirti which means
as famous as the moon in the sky
okay like how many people see the moon
on the full moon
it's famous the audience is big
for the full moon so they call it
chanda kirti chandra means moon right
and who's dharma kitty
he's another guy he wrote the most
important book on
on clear thinking okay i don't like to
call it
logic because it scares people clear
thinking
it's more a book about clear thinking
okay so tara mccarthy wrote that
me and ben cramer just started
the greatest commentary to that which is
a modern commentary
and it and we're going to finish in 56
years it's going to take 56 years we
have it scheduled
it's already scheduled so we have to
live at least 56 years more okay
uh so let's take a picture let's do
let's look at chandra kitty again
okay he wrote this book
about to explain the garjana which we're
gonna do
this next retreat we're gonna go deep
we call deep dive right and
uses the opening lines of his
explanation
called getting into the middle way okay
how to get into the middle ring
and they are very very important okay
the opening
lines of the godzilla
are extremely important and we're going
to spend a lot of time on that
but here we go here's
here's what they say
listeners sangee ding medium buddhist
new word for you guys medium buddhas
okay listeners
and medium buddhas
they come from the lords
the lords of the able ones
let's say it again listeners
and medium buddhas come from the lords
of the able ones the capable ones okay
and sange what's that
buddhas come from changju simbas
bodhisattvas okay two people
come from buddhas well where the buddhas
come
from well they come from bodhisattvas
and that's supposed to be
the opening lines of the greatest
commentary
nagarjuna ever okay so why what's he
trying to say
let's look at it again listeners
and medium buddhas come from
the lords of the able ones and the
buddhas
come from the bodhisattvas okay so he
quotes
chandra kirti now you guys are so lucky
why i
i personally like to take a vacation
inside
a retreat okay so i get into retreat you
guys are getting into retreat
we've been here for four or five days
me three seems like
uh four days
and we're starting to get deeper into
retreat at least i am i don't know about
you guys
probably you're just working harder but
you wear diamond mountain
people have done heavy retreats here you
know three year retreats here
you can't come to diamond mountain
and not feel like you're in retreat
already
and and i look forward i hope in the
fall
we can open up diamond mountain too to
everybody again
i think it's possible so
you can't be here without feeling like
you're already kind of in in retreat
right
don't you feel like that yeah it's a
very powerful place no
because of all the hard work that people
put here
to do retreat it has that flavor now
okay and uh then you start to think
about
you start to think about this this line
you know
what does it mean when you say that
that where buddhas come from you know
what does it mean when you start talking
about
where the buddhas come from and so
i thought that since we're at diamond
mountain
and since we reached these lines let's
do a mini retreat
okay gesla what do you mean
let's jump into chandi kirti for a few
days
for fun okay gesla the alarm room
already took 10 years
why are you adding time to it what
you're going to learn about lamrim
is that you never finish lumber okay
when you finish
one alarm maybe you just start over
again okay so
my opinion and my style let's go
deeper okay we reached these lines
of chandra kirti pablo buche thought it
was important
to teach them in the alarm room we're in
a retreat
mood because we're at diamond mountain
let's go deeper okay let's
let's leave the long rim and go
take a bath in chandi kirti for a couple
days
okay agree all right okay
and you can feel what's chande cutie
okay
and we're gonna use some copper's
commentary okay we're gonna jump in the
ocean
uh rick piguetto it's called the ocean
of clear thinking actually
and we're gonna we're gonna explore
these lines okay
because that has been done for 2 000
years
for 2 000 years when people got to this
part
of explaining the ganjana they stopped
and they went deeper okay so we're gonna
follow this tradition
okay i'm sorry and it means the long run
is gonna take longer
than i was supposed to all right here we
go
and what book of son kappa we're going
to use
we're not going to use his commentary
on nagarjuna which is what we're
translating nowadays
and that will be 1200 pages we are not
using
that commentary we are going to gombarap
so what's going
on so clarification of
illumination of gangba
the true thought the illumination of the
truth on okay and this
is not some copper's commentary on
on on the guardian of wisdom
it's on campus commentary on fifty
dollars
no on chandi kitty
okay he explains getting into the
middleweight
okay so we're gonna go to that book and
i'm working on that
book it'll be 3 000 pages or something
and i looked it up this morning i
started eight years ago
and and i'm one halfway through
something like that okay and if you're
complaining to me that i couldn't do
what you wanted me to do this week
it's because i have to finish that book
okay you have a choice you can give me
little things to do
and and you'll never get some copper's
book
or uh you can help me work on it give me
a couple hours a day that's all i need
okay just give me a couple days off per
day
a couple hours off per day to and i can
give it to you
okay and it's unbelievable it's
unbelievable so we are going to
sonica's commentary on
chandi kyuki okay why because pablo
granted started the trouble he
coded chandukati got it okay here we go
and don't think this is all repetitive
and don't think they all cover the same
thing they don't
they are extremely beautiful and deep
and if you want to see emptiness
this is like a very tasty way to do it
all right here we go so we're i still
gave you the text though you guys
right dilani you got dila nina
no i think i just glued it in i think
you
go straight on
uh it's in the projection text i sent
you
okay it's right after
okay good dilani okay
we're gonna cover this emptiness in two
parts dilania
can you show it you guys yay
okay ninja chan
he's gonna prove that to get to
bodhichitta
you have to get to compassion okay and
that's a reference to the
seven steps to
reach bodhichitta which is the next
retreat we're gonna do
after that other retreat okay
and we're going to study the seven-step
method
of reaching bodhichitta this retreat
we're covering the 10 cool things that
will happen to you
if you get bodhichitta that's what we're
doing this retreat
this retreat is a sales job
for getting buddy 10 then at the end of
this retreat you're supposed to say
okay i want one like a new tesla what do
you call those things
butterfly wing tesla uh
yeah i want one okay and then the next
retreat is to tell you how to get one
all right so we're just doing a sales
job all right
the next retreat we'll be talking about
the relationship
between compassion and buddhism okay
we'll get there
so so here we have uh
socopa saying look i'm gonna prove to
you
that to get to bodhichitta you have to
think about people's pain
you have to think about people's pain
that's the
that's the last thing you have to do to
get the body to
you have to think about other people's
pain okay
and and chang
temple he's also going to prove that
there are two other
causes two other things you need for
bodhichitta
but still compassion is still the root
okay thinking about other people's
trouble
is the root of bodhichitta in many
different ways let's put it that way
okay
so so i'm we're jumping into
that weird thing about people being born
from different things
we're jumping in there at compassion we
are jumping in at compassion
okay here we go tumbler
and don't forget this progression okay
don't forget these three points
okay
and i know it's difficult i know it
sounds complicated and i don't care
you have to know and you have to
discipline yourself
you can't say gisla it's too much for me
you can't you just teach something
simple give me something to recite
you know yeah i can it'll take you a
million years to get to buddhahood you
know
it's up to you it takes hard work we
what was the image for a hundred dollars
that we had
yeah yeah but we had a picture huh
no hard work it takes 12 years
we were talking about ati there was two
12 years by the way don't forget
one was atisha took 12 years where
in indonesia with his teacher
suvarna divipa of the golden isle
and then and then asanga
arya sang has sat in his cave for 12
years what's the point
it takes time okay it takes hard work
don't tell me you can't sit through
uh yeah there you go she's not going to
learn to do high dive
in uh after a half hour
mantra initiation it's not gonna happen
you need the hard work it takes many
years of hard work for mantra to work
requires many years of hard work okay
then a mantra will work okay
so anyway here we go so stay stay with
me don't be lazy
okay don't say ah it's too much it's a
lot
otherwise it wouldn't take a genius 12
years okay
right okay who had my trail sitting next
to him
okay
i don't even know if he didn't know he
was sitting next to
my chair right it seems to be a problem
okay double assume you're not need to
warn that kid so
how is it that
listeners and self-made buddhas okay
that's what medium buddha stands for
okay so you learned something new this
morning
there's a thing called the self-made
who's not
suffering good and a nickname for them
is medium buddha okay a medium and we're
gonna talk about it
okay and it's important to understand
and then there's uh
okay so there's three levels now we're
talking about
listener self-made buddha
and bodhisattva okay
listen listener self-made buddha
and bodhisattva three ways you can go
through your buddhist practice
three ways you can go listen their way
you can go self-made buddha also known
as
medium or you could go buddy something
okay three different ways to go through
your career
as a as a buddhist okay and he says
the first two come from buddhas they are
born from buddhists
okay if you want to get to be a listener
you need to find a buddha mommy
who can get pregnant and
give you birth okay seriously
and if you want to be a medium buddha
you got to find a real buddha mommy
to give you birth but now the big
question comes
where did the mommies come from
bodhichitta yeah bodhisattvas okay yeah
bodhisattvas okay
buddhas come from bodhisattvas okay
buddhas come from bodhisattvas buddhists
are born from
mommy which is bodhisattvas
where do those
lower practitioners come from they come
from the buddhists who got born from the
bodhisattvas
okay it's important okay that's where
we're going now in the alarm room
i didn't take us there pabonka did we're
just going deeper because we're at
diamond mountain
okay this is what we should do at thai
moment okay
all right try to be good so so that's
the first thing we're going to study
uh then we're going to study how is it
that bodhichitta is the mommy or
bodhisattvas
are the mommies of the buddhas okay and
then
we're gonna look at
what's the main thing you need to get to
be a bodhisattva
okay so here we go
and then some copper quotes chanted okay
and get used to the names don't tell me
don't tell me
you don't have enough memory to remember
these three guys
okay you can do it there's nagarjuna
there's there's
some kappa and then there's okay it's
okay you can remember
okay it's not that hard all right the
guardian wrote the
mother book called wisdom
and then chanda kirti wrote entering the
middleweight
and then socapa wrote the ocean and then
tony lama gave us a
boat okay
and it's funny when charlie lama starts
his book he says you're gonna drown in
the gardener
sorry you're going to drown in socappa
if you don't have my ship
he does a sales job for his ship okay
and we're translating all of those okay
we're translating tendu kenti while we
translate
uh some cuppa and we're translating the
guardian a while we translate challenge
okay we're translating all four right
now
so so if i'm not available to do
something
smaller please bear with me okay
i i'm i'm making uh what do you call
priority decisions
you know like should the world not have
this or should the world not have this
and those are decisions i have to make
but
don't hassle me okay i mean you can
remind me that i didn't do what you
wanted but
don't get too serious i do have a plan
i have a master plan do you know this
song
we'll play it or we can't play it the
creator
[Music]
why do we call listeners listeners
okay why do we call listeners
listeners okay say srabaka
okay shravaka is the sanskrit okay
shavukah means
listener someone who's listening okay
and that's the first of these three
kinds of practitioners we call three
tracks right
listener self-made buddha or
medium good all right and then buddy
self-attract okay
so why do they call those guys listeners
there's the classic
explanation and then there's the
traditional explanation
okay so we'll get there okay don't worry
about it
we'll get there uh
here's the traditional explanation and
later we'll do the classical explanation
okay
which one is more important
i'd say the classical one which i have
taught you before
but here's a traditional one okay
there are people in the world
who listen to good teachings
from other people okay they listen to
good teachings
from other people gombe debu
then they meditate on those teachings
as a result debu okay paula
as a fruit of that hard work
they reached listener buddhahood
list you can call it listener
enlightenment it's not
full enlightenment it's called listener
enlightenment
okay so there's three kinds of
there's an enlightenment for each one of
these three which is the real
enlightenment the bodhisattva one but we
still call the other two an
enlightenment actually they are just
kinds of nirvana okay kinds of numbers
okay
and they can
they can be an instrument for other
people listening to those same teachings
so we call them listen
okay they learn good teachings they
practice them
they get to nirvana and they help
other people listen to them therefore
they are called
listeners okay got it
so it's a little more complicated than
you might guess
okay what's a listener yes no
they they get teachings they practice
them
they become reach their own
enlightenment which is nirvana
and then they help other people listen
to those teachings and then
that's why they're listeners okay got it
that's
the traditional
explanation but not the classic one
classic's higher than traditional right
in my opinion you know they don't say
rock traditions they say rock classics
right
so okay all right okay
uh that's all we're gonna do on that and
i listen i know it's complicated
and i know it's not easy
but if you really want to do something
with your life
you know you only get a little time to
do something with your life
trust me you know right jimmy you only
get a little time here
to do something cool and if you learn
this thing
you can really help others you can do
something cool with your life okay
all right